Register of the Robert Daniel Murphy papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Oversize File II, 1933-1975 (Box 179)
  - Certificates (Box 182)
    - "Officers and men of the United Nations Command extend best wishes to Ambassador Robert D. Murphy and express to him their thanks for his unselfish sacrifices and invaluable support in the crusade for the preservation of human freedom in the Far East," signed by Mark W. Clark, Commander in Chief, United States Army, undated
    - Title of the Knight of the Cross by General Franco of Spain, undated
    - President Franklin D. Roosevelt, appointing Robert D. Murphy service officer of class one, 1940 September 3
    - Department of State – one for official recognition and appreciation for completion of thirty years of service, 1949 July, and one for distinguished service, 1949 October 12
      Includes program, handwritten note, pin, and photograph
    - President Harry S. Truman, appointing Robert Murphy ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary of the United States of America to Belgium, 1949 September 22
    - President Dwight D. Eisenhower, appointing Robert Murphy assistant secretary of state, 1953 March 20
    - President Dwight D. Eisenhower, appointing Robert Murphy a foreign service officer of the class of career ambassador of the United States of America, 1956 March 7
    - Catholic University of America, conferring upon Robert Murphy a degree of honorary doctor of laws, 1957 June 9
    - University of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, conferring upon Robert Murphy the degree of doctor of civil law, 1957 June 12
    - Albert Benjamin Chandler, Governor of the Commonwealth of Kentucky, recognizing Robert Murphy a commissioned Kentucky colonel, 1959 April 1
    - College of St. Joseph, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, conferring upon Robert Murphy a degree of honorary doctor of laws, 1959 June 7
    - President Dwight D. Eisenhower, appointing Robert Murphy under secretary of state for political affairs, 1959 August 12
    - National Press Club, "in recognition of meritorious service to correspondents of press, radio, and television in the nation's capital,", 1959 December 1
    - Resolution adopted by the Board of Directors of the American Foreign Service Association "to express deep appreciation of unstinting service to his country and for major contribution to the profession of diplomacy,", 1959 December 3
    - Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun by the Emperor of Japan, 1960 (Box 183)
    - Pope John XXIII, conferring on Robert Murphy the Great Cross of the Order of St. Gregory the Great, 1960 February 12
    - Honorary membership in the Fellows of the American Bar Foundation "in recognition of distinguished contributions both to diplomacy and law,", 1960 February 20
    - Colgate University, Hamilton, New York, conferring upon Robert D. Murphy honorary doctor of laws, 1960 June 13
    - President of the Federal Republic of Germany, bestowing upon Robert D. Murphy the Grand Cross of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany "in appreciation and recognition of the very large contribution made by Americans to international understanding," 1961 July 8. Includes a letter from v. Rhamm, 1961 August 23, a certificate in English, and a note, 1961 October 13
    - Order of Lafayette, presenting its Freedom Award to Robert D. Murphy, 1964 February 10
    - Resolution passed by the Board of Directors of the Gillette Company "in recognition of Robert D. Murphy's vision and sensitivity on international matters during the period of his association with the Board," Boston, Massachusetts, 1965 March 18
    - Member of the National Export Expansion Council from 1969 July 1 to 1971 June 30
    - Sylvanus Thayer medal certificate awarded to Robert Murphy, 1974 May 7
      See also boxes 161 and 177
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews, conferring upon Robert D. Murphy the Charles Evans Hughes Award "for courageous leadership in governmental, civic, and humanitarian affairs,", 1975 December 23
  - Christmas cards (Box 184)
    - Painting and card from President and Mrs. Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1959
    - Painting of the White House with a note describing the American elm planted by President Woodrow Wilson as "a symbol of peace and serenity" in the north portico of the White House, from President and Mrs. Lyndon Johnson, 1966
    - Picture of a decorated tree and a fireplace with a message from President and Mrs. Lyndon Johnson and signed by the president, 1967
    - Reproduction of Abraham Lincoln by George P. A. Healy and a note conveying a message of good will, from President and Mrs. Richard Nixon, 1971
  - Photographs (Box 185)
    See also Photographs
    - 3 black and white and 1 color print of a drawing of Robert Murphy from Time magazine cover, undated
    - 1 portrait of Robert Murphy, undated
    - 1 portrait of President Harry S. Truman sitting at a desk, undated
    - 1 print depicting Bernard Law Montgomery with three other individuals, undated
    - 1 print signed by President Gerald Ford, depicting Robert Murphy and the president sitting in the White House with other unidentified individuals, given to Robert Murphy with the message, "with appreciation and best wishes,", undated (Box 186)
    - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy sitting at a table with Robert B. Dabie, John Foster Dulles, Herbert Hoover, Jr., Douglas MacArthur II, Livingstone Merchant, Thurston B. Morton, Robert McCardle, Roderick L. O'Connor, Herman Phleger, Walters S. Robertson, and Bedell Smith, undated
    - 1 print depicting James Byrnes and signed by him, undated
    - 1 print depicting President Lyndon Johnson, undated
    - 1 print depicting Omar Bradley, undated
    - 1 print depicting President Herbert Hoover, undated
    - 1 print depicting George C. Marshall, undated
    - 1 print depicting Francis Cogwell, naval attaché, United States Navy, Paris, 1939
    - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with Dean Acheson, John Foster Dulles, Carter Magruder, Paul Nitze, Fritz Oppenheimer, and others as part of the U. S. Delegation to the Four-Power Conference, Paris, 1949 Spring
    - 1 print depicting L. G. Cardinal Cicogriani, 1958 December 8
    - 1 print depicting Antonio(?), 1959 January 10
    - 11 prints depicting Robert Murphy with President Lyndon Johnson, Robert McNamara, and other unidentified individuals, 1967-1968(?)
    - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Sterling Brown, Oscar Straus, and William Fay, at the meeting of national co-chairmen of the National Council of Christians and Jews, Building for Brotherhood, New York, 1969 January 3
    - 1 print depicting President Richard Nixon along with other unidentified individuals, 1972 May 5
    - 1 print depicting President Richard Nixon, 1971 May 6
  - Posters and paintings
    - Poster depicting George Washington, undated
    - Painting depicting 5 individuals in Japanese style, undated
    - Painting of a Japanese lady dressed in traditional Japanese attire, 1969 May 9
  - Printed matter (Box 187)
    - "American Press Reaction to the Franco-Tunisian Crisis,", 1958
    - Review of Diplomat among Warriors, Saturday Evening Post, 1964 February 22
    - "Up Front with Robert Murphy," C. L. Sulzberger, New York Times Book Review, 1964 February 23
    - Le Monde et la Vie, 1965
    - The Saturday Evening Post, 1968 August 24
  - Scrapbooks, 1933-1968 (Box 188)
    - Volume of clippings relating to Robert Murphy's accomplishments in North Africa and Germany and to the academic honors bestowed upon him, 1933-1949
      Also includes clippings describing daughter Rosemary Murphy's appearance in German films. Cover has sketch of Robert Murphy by Frank Wright
    - Two volumes of clippings describing Robert Murphy's activities and accomplishments during his service as ambassador to Japan, 1952 – 1953 July (Box 189)
    - Volume of clippings relating to Robert Murphy's selection as President Richard Nixon's aide during the transition from the Johnson to the Nixon administration, 1968 November
- Photographs II, 1900-1976
  1201 prints, and 1 negative, depicting Robert Murphy and personalities such as John Foster Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Louis Mountbatten, Richard Nixon, Helmut Schmidt, and Albert C. Wedemeyer.
  - 1 print depicting unidentified individuals and Robert Murphy writing on a piece of paper put against a man's back. Attached to a Christmas card from Fred and Ben Hauserman, undated (Box-folder 190: 1)
  - 1 framed print depicting a young Robert Murphy(?), undated
  - 6 prints, including 3 depicting a group of individuals standing in front of a building, 1 print depicting a mountain range, and 2 prints depicting a house, undated
  - 2 prints depicting unidentified individuals, undated (Box-folder 190: 2)
  - 1 print depicting Albert C. Wedemeyer with an unidentified individual, undated
  - 2 prints, one depicting a lady entering the Department of State building, the other showing her talking to Robert Murphy and pointing to a world map on the wall, undated
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy and a group of unidentified individuals holding diplomas, possibly in a graduation ceremony, undated (Box-folder 190: 3)
  - 2 prints, with a card from Rev. Theodore M. Hesburgh attached, depicting Robert Murphy shaking hands with a person holding a diploma, undated
  - 5 prints depicting Robert Murphy giving a speech, possibly in a church, and talking to others inside a building, undated
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with the ambassador of Argentina and Sam Wough, undated
  - 6 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy sitting with others, 1 print of a lady taking the oath of office with Robert Murphy watching, 1 print of three ladies and 2 men standing with Robert Murphy in front of flags, 1 print of Robert Murphy shaking hands with someone, 1 print of Robert Murphy standing and surrounded by others, and 1 print of Robert Murphy talking to José de Cubric(?), undated (Box-folder 190: 4)
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with John A. Coleman, Terence Cardinal Cooke, and Sterling W. Brown at a religious leaders dinner, New York, undated (Box-folder 190: 5)
  - 2 prints depicting people sitting inside a beautifully decorated church, undated
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with the Chinese ambassador and his wife, undated (Box-folder 190: 6)
  - 9 prints depicting Robert Murphy during his visit to Tunisia, undated
  - 4 prints depicting a group of people walking in rain with a lady holding an umbrella, undated
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy talking to an Asian individual, undated (Box-folder 190: 7)
  - 4 prints depicting Robert Murphy with unidentified ladies and gentlemen, including one in which he is sitting in a car, undated
  - 4 prints, including 1 of Robert Murphy with Bandaranaike, Prime Minister of Ceylon, William Roundtree, and others; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with Helmut Schmidt, Federal Republic of Germany; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with others; and 1 print of Frank W. Clark, undated (Box-folder 190: 8)
  - 16 prints and 1 negative depicting Robert Murphy and other unidentified individuals, undated (Box-folder 190: 9)
  - 4 prints of Robert Murphy and William Bessell, Mark Boatner, and Walter L. Lambeth, undated (Box-folder 190: 10)
  - 1 print of Robert Murphy with Byington, Higgins, McGregor, and Wisemeyer, undated
  - 21 prints depicting a group of soldiers carrying rifles and flags near a column bearing names of different U.S. states, undated (Box-folder 190: 11)
  - 5 prints depicting Robert Murphy with unidentified individuals sitting on a dais, giving a speech, and walking along the ocean by a ship at anchor, undated
  - 4 prints, including 2 depicting an individual in military uniform sitting in a chair, and 2 depicting an individual giving a speech, undated (Box-folder 190: 12)
  - 5 prints depicting individuals placing wreath near a casket and Robert Murphy watching, undated
  - 10 prints depicting Robert Murphy sitting at a table with others, a group of people gathered in an open area and sitting outside or under a tent, and Robert Murphy trying to unlock a door, undated
  - 5 prints, including 1 depicting a building by the side of the road, 2 prints depicting cranes, and 2 depicting a ship, undated
  - 1 album of 23 prints depicting Robert Murphy and others, given to him by the minister for foreign affairs, Lebanon, undated (Box-folder 191: 1)
  - 6 print depicting Robert Murphy with unidentified individuals, undated
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, circa 1900 (Box-folder 191: 2)
  - 1 print of Fred W. Weinecke, 1911
  - 1 print, a group photograph of Marquette University Law School night class students, 1915
  - 3 prints depicting a tower on an elevated platform surrounded by trees and walls, 1930
  - 1 print depicting the American government building, Paris, France, 1933 November
  - 2 prints, including 1 depicting a group of individuals sitting around tables, Automotive Club of Europe, Paris, France, 1935 October, and the other depicting one lady sitting in a chair surrounded by one young woman and two young girls, France, 1936 July
  - 3 prints including 1 depicting the Duke of Windsor on the occasion of his marriage, Chateau de Candé, Paris, France, 1937 June 3, and 2 depicting the Pere Marquette Monument, Laon, France, 1937 June 13 (Box-folder 191: 3)
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with a lady, Chantilly race track, Prix de Diane, 1939 June 4
  - 1 print listing names of people attending a liberation meeting, 1942 October 22
  - 1 print depicting Brigadier General Jerry V. Matejka, Governor General Chattel of Algeria, and his wife, at their palace in North Africa, 1942 December 5
  - 8 prints depicting atrocities committed by the Germans at a concentration camp, Gotha, Germany, 1945 May 3(?)
  - 1 print, a sketch of Casa del Marqués de Santa Rosa, Cordoba, with Christmas message from Mr. and Mrs. Frank Manito, 1945 December 29
  - 15 prints depicting Robert Murphy and others on the occasion of his appointment as ambassador to Belgium, 1949 (Box-folder 191: 4)
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy addressing the joint meeting of the Board of Directors of the U.S. Educational Foundation in the Netherlands, 1950 May 24
  - 3 prints depicting Robert Murphy at a cocktail party hosted by him for Belgian officers at the U.S. Embassy, 1950 June 22
  - 1 print sent from Prague depicting Ambassador and Mrs. Briggs, 1950 August
  - 7 prints depicting Robert Murphy and Mrs. Murphy at a cocktail party in honor of the American Women's Club, USIS building, 1950 September 11
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy at firing exercises at Lombaardzijde (Belgian Coast), 1950 October (Box-folder 190: 5)
  - 5 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy visiting Headquarters, European Command, 1950 Oct 17; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy in General Hauly's office on the occasion of Paul Hoffman's visit, 1950 October 18; and 3 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Moreau de Melen, 1950 October 19
  - 25 prints, including 23 depicting Robert Murphy, Mrs. Murphy, their daughter, and others at Kipushi, Katanga, Belgian Congo, and 4 prints depicting Robert Murphy passing through Leopoldville, 1950 November
  - Album of 39 prints presented to Robert Murphy as a souvenir during his visit to the Provincial Technical School at de Verviers, 1951 May 28
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with de Schryver, Theunis, and Gutt, "Groenhof," Belsele (Waas), 1951 August 21 (Box-folder 191: 6)
  - 11 prints of Robert Murphy with other unidentified individuals at the International Fair on American Day, Ghent, Belgium, 1951 September 18
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy at a reception hosted by him at his residence in honor of the Chamber of Commerce, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1951 September 21
  - 5 prints, including Robert Murphy addressing American Fulbright grantees at a dinner in their honor at the Fondation Universitaire, and Hugh Millard and Pierre Frieden giving speeches on the same occasion, 1951 September 25
  - 10 prints, including 2 depicting Robert Murphy with William Feitelberg and Antoine Seyle, and 8 prints of Robert Murphy with Mildred Murphy, Sylvia Stahlman (Mme Bardi), and others at a USIS party in honor of Giula Bardi at the Embassy residence, 1951 September 26 (Box-folder 191: 7)
  - 16 prints depicting Robert Murphy, Mrs. Murphy, and their daughter, Mildred, including prints taken during Cardinal Spellman's visit to Tokyo; and Robert Murphy's visit with Mr. Nishida, Mr. T. Yoneda, Mr. T. Ontan; and Mrs. Nakai, Mrs. Hollington Tong, Mrs. Ronald Tong and others at a tea party held in honor of Mrs. Murphy, 1952 June-December
  - 1 print depicting Mark W. Clark, 1952 June 26
  - 9 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy taking the oath of office as assistant secretary of state for United Nations affairs(?), 1953 July; 3 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Ananthakrishnan and Hamilton on the occasion of the Diplomatic Tennis Tournament, 1953 October; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy speaking before the State Convention of the Texas Congress of Parents and Teachers, San Antonio, Texas, 1953 November 19; and 4 prints depicting Robert Murphy with John J. Cavanaugh, Bernard C. Duffy, Theodore M. Hesburgh, E. Lovitz, James A. Mulvey, Sylvan Oestreicher, and Victor D. Ziminsky at the President's Committee of Notre Dame annual dinner, New York City, 1953 December 9 (Box-folder 191: 8)
  - 5 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy at the National Conference of Christians and Jews, New York City, on the occasion of the Brotherhood Award, 1954; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy during a visit of the Kalmuk, 1954 January(?), 1 print depicting Robert Murphy meeting with the representatives of the Ukrainian Church of U.S.A. (John Romanition, Francois E. Stevens, Archbishop Mystyslav Skyrypnyk, and Rev. D. Leschishin) 1954 August 13; 1 print of Robert Murphy's meeting with Chinese POWs, 1954 September; and 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with James B. Cohant and Prof. Walter Hallstein during a short visit to the Palais Schaumburg, Bonn, 1954 September 13
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy, deputy under secretary of state, and John Hollister, director of the International Cooperation Administration, New York international airport, 1955 March (Box-folder 191: 9)
  - 3 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy receiving an award from Wisconsin high school students, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1955 April 15; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy and the Italian ambassador depositing the ratification of protocol on Germany's admission to NATO, 1955 April 20; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy visiting Latin American diplomats at the annual Memorial Day Speedway Race, Indianapolis, Indiana, 1955 May
  - 3 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy at the commencement ceremony at Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., 1955 June 6; 1 print depicting his appearance at the "Youth Wants to Know," television show, 1955 June 17(?), and 1 print of Robert Murphy given to him as a memento of the Marshall Plan luncheon, 1955 June 20 (Box-folder 191: 10)
  - 3 prints, including 1 depicting Robert Murphy's swearing in ceremony as deputy under secretary of state with John Foster Dulles and John Simmons; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy shaking hands with unidentified individuals; and 1 print depicting an unidentified individual's swearing in ceremony, 1955 August 12
  - 4 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Randolph Burgess, Joseph Dodge, Alfred M. Gruenther, George Hunphrey, Ridgeway Knight, General Lauris Norstad, and Samuel Waugh, visiting SHAEF and Allied Headquarters near Paris to confer with the Supreme Allied Commander Europe, General Gruenther, 1955 September 19 (Box-folder 192: 1)
  - 12 prints depicting Robert Murphy with others during his visit to Belgrade, 1955 October (Box-folder 192: 2)
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy meeting with Japanese representatives of the League of Bonin Islands evacuees, 1955 October 20(?) (Box-folder 192: 3)
  - 2 prints of Robert Murphy with other unidentified individuals, 1955 October-November
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy with the Mexican ambassador, 1955 November 18
  - 9 prints depicting Robert Murphy and Mrs. Murphy with John Foster Dulles, Loy Henderson, John Simmons, and others, 1956 April 9 (Box-folder 192: 4)
  - 1 print signed by Cecil Gibbon, deputy speaker, National Assembly, Pakistan, 1956 May 25
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with the World Affairs Program winners of Minneapolis Star and Tribune, 1956 June 22
  - 2 prints depicting the signing of the U.S.-Austrian atomic energy bilateral treaty, 1956 June 28
  - 1 print of Robert Murphy with the ambassador of Sudan, 1956 August; 1 print depicting Robert Murphy laying the foundation stone with a hammer in his hand at Kongresshalle Berlin, 1956 October 3 (Box-folder 192: 5)
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Ahmed Benabucl, Leon Benzaquen, Moulay Hassan, Rachid Moulina, El-Mehdi Ben Aboud, and Aovad, and 2 prints of Robert Murphy with James S. Plant and John F. Simmons, 1956 November 28 (Box-folder 192: 6)
  - 2 prints of Robert Murphy with Jose Loteto, Dempster McIntosh, and Cesar Gonzales, 1956 Nov 29
  - 2 prints of Robert Murphy presenting an outstanding performance rating award to Richard Spells, 1956 December 20, and 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Helen F. Doran and Assistant Secretary Wilcox, 1956 December 21 (Box-folder 192: 7)
  - 1 print of Robert Murphy and others at the cornerstone laying ceremony of the new State Department building, 1957 January 5, and 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with W. C. Daniel and Luke E. Hart, 1957 January 18 (Box-folder 192: 8)
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy at the communion breakfast, Loyola Retreat House, Washington, D.C., 1957 March 3
  - 1 print of Robert Murphy speaking at Georgetown University, taken by the Georgetown Record, 1957 April, and 1 print of Dwight D. Eisenhower taken in North Africa and given to Robert Murphy, 1957 April 9(?)
  - 3 prints depicting Robert Murphy shaking hands with and participating in the ceremonial oath with Gerald A. Drew and Victor Purse, 1957 May 6, and 1 print of Frances E. Wells being congratulated by Robert Murphy on her confirmation as ambassador to Norway, 1957 May 17 (Box-folder 192: 9)
  - 1 print depicting Robert Murphy at the award ceremony at the Catholic University of America, 1957 June 9, and 1 print of Robert Murphy at the luncheon hosted by him in honor of the ambassador of Yugoslavia, Carlton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1957 June 19
  - 1 print of the North African Panoe Club's second session, 1957 August 22(?)
  - 2 prints depicting Robert Murphy with Walter Robertson, Mr. Fujiyama, Japanese foreign minister, and Ambassador Asakai, 1957 September (Box-folder 192: 10)
  - 2 prints of Robert Murphy affixing the seal and presenting William Hopkins with the presidential proclamation naming October 11 as a day of commemoration for General Casimir Pulaski; and 1 print depicting Robert Murphy affixing the seal and presenting Walter Walmsley with his commission as career minister in the Foreign Service of the United States; 1 print of Murphy giving a speech, and 1 print of Robert Murphy with an unidentified woman, 1957 September 16
  - 1 print of Robert Murphy and others at the 15th reunion of the North African Peace Club, 1957 October 21
  - 4 prints depicting Robert Murphy and others at the Foreign Service luncheon at Fort McNair for I. W. Carpenter before he left the State Department, 1957 December (Box-folder 192: 11)